[Music]
hello everyone this is Frank defus and
welcome to holot talk the internet's
laser and holography talk show enjoyed
in over 42 countries throughout the
world and now here's this week's
[Music]
show hello Triple T hi Joy how are you
it's Frank hi how you doing doing pretty
good good you're all set then right yep
how are you I'm doing good you're
probably doing better out there than you
would out here with all the snowstorms
we've gotten so far yep I was just
talking to my sister out there and she
was shoveling this morning I'm beat yep
I'm beat I don't miss that part it's not
even it's not even win yet it's still
fall I know yeah you don't usually get
it until January yeah well I'm glad you
decided to come on the on the on the
show first I I would just want to
explain to the listeners that I had
promised to bring you on because I
wanted to do something specifically with
you for two areas your your triple take
holographics business that you have
since we're in the holiday season now
full swing and also I believe you're
involved with a number of different uh
professional organizations I believe
it's women in Optics and things of that
nature right right so we can talk a
little bit about both of those how's
that okay now you came into this
starting triple takes you already you
already had a professional background in
holography in fact you weren't too far
from me you were up in Elmsford New York
for a while right that's right great
what was your capacity up there with the
uh American bank note um essentially I
was the holograph that's the title and
what it meant is that I was the person
who took the artwork that was already uh
developed from the art department and I
actually put it on the table and created
the master hologram okay and after that
it was sent off to the production floor
for the embossing mhm and you know I was
up at American back note whole graph
Graphics up in the 80s I I guess you
weren't there at the time someone took
me down into the studio uhhuh was denish
there as well uh he would have been
coming along I think in
86 so it might have been still earlier
than that yeah I I wonder if he was the
one that took me down um it was most
likely uh Lenny I think's been there for
a long time and he's the the lab manager
was he who was the one that did the um
Michael Jordan cover for sports illustra
oh that would have been Todd okay cuz I
he he actually visited here one time
okay I had him autograph one of the uh
one of the Sports Illustrated covers
yeah so did I did you yeah about time
holograph signed their work
yeah so you're probably doing what is
the most difficult job to do in
holography today and that and that is
running a small business absolutely what
are what are some of the products the
two of you put together and you might
want to just go over quickly both of
your roles and responsibilities within
the uh the business that you have um
well as far as the the products that
we're producing we can in fact make
almost any kind of polyram um we have
the capability and the knowledge to do
so um what you'll find on our website is
primarily the
dcg which I have uh partnered in with a
lot of Art Glass in order to create uh
products that that are more salable
because people would I mean people will
buy a coaster anyway but what they look
for is the decorative aspect of the
coaster and so if we put a hologram on
it it's not a super high art thing but
it's interesting that they core thing
that we have a lot of people interested
in so that's what kind of stuff we make
clocks coasters keychains you know the
usual uh assortment
ofs now these items that you create
they're not there's no automation
involved in this process at all they're
all made by hand is that correct yes
they're all Handmade by our own two
little fingers as far as the well
actually I guess 20 fingers the uh
actual holography starts with um most of
the time the actual image is inspired by
someone who wants something um then I'll
put together some kind of a model or
artwork uh we set it up on the table
denesh loves to do the chemistry part so
I like to do the geometry part which
works out really well for the two of us
I go in and set up the table and then he
shoots the Holograms and develops them
and comes up with all of those um kinds
of
uh parameters and then we seal it um
into the glass and then I go into the
back and shape it into whatever shape
it's going to be into whether it be
coaster actually I can do some very uh
elaborate things sometimes I put the the
gold guilding Edge or you know depends
on what we want to do with
it now where would someone find your
products other than the website or are
there um commercial outlets that uh
retailers that are stocking anything um
I don't have any commercial outlets but
we have worked with other people who
have had us make something for them that
they have sold again on the private
Market um we've made some things for
rayel um there's um a couple of internal
things we've done for um the Navy has
had um various at uh things that they do
they um like the the ball or something
they'll have this big Gala event and
then we made the gifts that were handed
out to the guests there yeah um that
sort of thing so it's largely internal
one of the things when I said you know
about figuring out a business
is it's it's even harder it's hard
enough to make to make the product
harder to make a business and even
harder that still to figure out what the
public is going to want so most of what
we've done is to have the public come to
us and say this is what we want and then
we go make it yeah I imagine the
majority of people that are going to be
listening to the show would be people
who are already doing Holograms to begin
with Al although there is a a pretty
large cross-section of of people who
listen to the show such as Educators
students and things of that
nature
um on a scale of 1 to 10 how difficult
is it day by day I mean the hours must
be long and and and the work must be
grueling
sometimes um it depends I mean as you
said especially since most of these guys
are making Holograms themselves you
realize that you know if you love what
you're doing you don't count the hours
um mostly I do well to some extent I
mean because we're trying to make a
business the more important thing is
counting the money at least today I
would yeah well today is a snowy day for
you so you'd want to stay
in I'd probably be shooting today if I
were at home some of my some of my
brightest Holograms have happened when
I've shot them on the nights of
snowstorms yep cuz I live in Center City
and it actually dampens the entire
geographical area yeah I bet it would
that' be
nice so have a relatively stable area
here because most of the under layman is
granite I see I see you our table does
float if we need really long exposures
oh so one of those nice Newport tables
oh that's nice that's nice actually I
understand there's a few hands that have
had us before because it has a a strange
feature in the middle of it a cut out
and other people coming in here have
looked at that and said I've seen that
table somewhere before
huh do you work in your home no um we
have a whole separate Studio oh do you
it's about 4,000 square feet decent
really decent size um it is actually the
studio that Don Broadbent was in okay we
met up with him uh I guess about 7even
years ago is as long as we've been in
San Diego and he was um someone we'd
never met before we'd heard through
other people that he was selling off
equipment because he wanted to retire so
we met up with him and we actually um
got him uh a brief uh job at the place
where we were working with which was a
photonics company at the time and so we
sort of started getting together and
then we started thinking that we'd love
to make our own business on the side so
we actually kind of moved in with Don
here at this studio with the idea that
we were going to do like a transition
thing until he retired
um because he was going to be moving
away and so we eventually did that and
in 2000 February 2000 we took over
entirely and became triple Tes I see and
Don is still lurking out there um I
believe he's in Arizona now so if
anybody's trying to get in touch with
him I know how to find him well that
that truly is a business that that
you're running there that you have your
own location and everything for it do
you have a display area that folks could
come in and see Holograms um there's a
small display area we have a private
collection um because I like to collect
other holographs work as well so some of
the things are actually at home um but
we do have a display area here um mostly
our products um but also a few other
pieces that um we've collected along the
way that are from other holographs that
have actually come into the studio or
students that have worked here um and
couple of my favorite pieces from people
that are a little more friends
than you know we have uh a Bogman from
Richmond Studios mhm that uh was one of
my favorites long before I ever knew
where it came from and when Edina
finally gave me a copy of it that was
one of my treasured pieces and I have it
up here at the lab as well did you say
Linda man yes yes yeah there's there's
someone down by Philadelphia that
actually is it on film or is it on glass
plate it's on film yeah um and I framed
it in a regular glass frame yeah there's
there's there's someone down in
Philadelphia uh in New Hope Pennsylvania
that has one on display in a down there
that's an actual glass
plate is that the 3D shop out in the
Anish
Village uh no no you're probably
thinking more towards Lancaster this
this is more towards the Delaware River
down by Philadelphia it's a small town
called New Hope yeah well I know the
area I have cousin there his name's yeah
Howard Kur is his name I think it's
laser Illusions or something is the uh
is the shop but it's it's one of the
shops he he has a wonderful collection
of holograms there and a lot of them
were on glass plates
uh but in order to stay afloat you know
with some of those shops you have to
have a lot of different novelty items as
well right you know along with it so
it's a it's a a mix of a lot of
different things there and we've been
getting a lot of calls from people that
said that have been saying that you know
I used to be able to get stickers and I
used to be able to get this and
everything where do you get it anymore
and so there's definitely a lot of room
out there for that kind of thing because
you know there are people out there that
want it and don't know where to go
anymore
because even when I started up in
holography seriously I mean when I
actually got my first job in it already
you know all of the schools were closed
all of the galleries were closed you
know there was just this big black hole
Yeah Yeah in holography and I think
right now especially with the internet
and and these sorts of things getting
out there there's more and PE more and
more people getting involved and there's
more people who know what it is yeah
absolutely you know if we can just get
the the public a little more involved
again you know there might be a
Resurgence there may be yeah or we may
see it you know the technology just you
know it's it's a it's a competing
technology and there are a lot of
Technologies competing with it so uh I
was down at the uh you know where Cam in
New Jersey is right yeah yeah I was down
at the new aquarium you know they closed
the State Aquarium I think a private
Venture took it over uh and they put in
a new uh 3D theater so I had the
opportunity of seeing my first 3D film
film shot
underwater and oh I I I was expecting to
go in there to see something um rather
crass you know as far as H technology is
concerned and effect but it was gorgeous
I mean it was just absolutely it was
like you were engulfed in in in the
actual movie itself it yeah I love those
new theaters they they're mostly they're
put out by IMAX but it's a completely
different design than the old IMAX domes
that know used to be Planetarium and the
effect is fabulous yeah I think the
polarization was involved with the uh
left left and right View and things that
out here they're actually calling it 4D
4D huh we laugh about that oh yeah yeah
cuz there was yeah there was Motion in
the seats uhhuh and you would get
sprayed with water as well that's right
so I guess you know it's great if
anybody you know can get near one of
these you know I think there's one in
Harrisburg also but I haven't actually
been there that can run these 3D uh
Polaroid type uh displays and it's worth
it yeah you got to go to these places
just just don't need any cheap Philly
hot dogs before you go in you know so
you also mentioned workshops maybe do do
you run workshops that uh um people can
come to working with the local pelomar
College okay and so what they do is that
they're the ones who organize and do all
the advertising to get the students in
and then we run the workshops mhm and
that's been really a lot of fun uh we
can only take about three or four
students at a time in the lab obviously
because we've only got so much working
room um but we've gotten some good
response and the people that have come
have just been thrilled that they've
never done such a thing before is making
a hologram and and of course we love
teaching yeah I started doing the
workshops here in ' 83 and from I'd say
late elementary middle school kids all
the way up into uh retirees uhhuh yeah
in fact actually I think most of our our
students have been older MH there was
only one younger kid and even that
wasn't you know a kid he was I think 25
yeah um so that and I think that speaks
also about the the form or Glory of
holography is that the people who
understand what it really is and really
have always wanted to do that is the
older generation and I'd like to really
reach out to the younger generation and
get them more involved in recognizing
what the medium can do yeah and not just
you know keyy little stickers you know
for their notebooks mhm why used to run
the uh laser holography workshops at a
place in Philadelphia called the
Franklin Institute uhhuh so I was down
there for about 10 years and that was a
gifted and talented program that would
come in there for workshops and they
were all all young students that would
come in for that uhuh and uh oh Jesus is
going back a long long time maybe I
could have been one of those students I
well I'll tell you what I recently just
had one of the students come back with
one of their own children uhuh so I'm
sort of like a grand teacher yeah you
know like that feel great yeah it's it
was a wonderful I I to to be honest with
you I I can't remember the person you
know I mean they're grown and they say
you know they're in a workshop but you
can't remember who they are really I
mean because it's it's not like you have
them for a year or two years you have
them for two or three hours on a Sunday
afternoon and then you never see them
again you know 20 years ago or whatever
but it's it is a nice feeling to be in
the second generation of it now
MH women in addition to uh running our
normal workshops with the the college we
also have done some professional
lectures for uh for companies that are
working in photonics um for the the
colleges themselves in their colloquia
and and things like that so we you know
that's feeding up into the the higher
Consulting that we're also doing you
always have to keep an eye out when you
have your own business for other work oh
of course it's a very delicate process
I'd say maybe I think in 1993 I went on
my own entirely with holography MH and
um that was probably an early mistake
that I made was that uh while you're
doing the work you not only have to do
the work but you constantly have to be
looking for work that's further on down
the line yes because once all of the
work that you finally you know that you
have is
complete all of a sudden you hit a wall
because you haven't been looking for
other work to come in and it's a it's a
very difficult balance to maintain yeah
and both jobs can be fulltime absolutely
how to squeeze them all in yes yeah if
you're working in March you've got to be
you've got to be arranging things for
July you know that's right yeah what's
your involvement with women in Optics I
saw a picture on your website of a group
that got together I guess it must be
must have been a dinner in New York or
something it was actually at SBI um and
we always have at all of the different
um Optics conventions they do have a
little lunch in where they get together
M and the primary function really of the
women in Optics is to support women
doing research specifically that we can
help fund their way to uh giving a
lecture at one of these
conferences and that's really the the
primary function is just to to give
women the opportunity to step up in the
in the Optics world and present
themselves and become you know better
known and better established
professionals I imagine you also have
Outreach educational outreach program
available for high school students as
well or no I I don't actually know that
much because I'm not one of the
organizers um I'm just sort of one of
the members and I showed up at the
luncheons and that sort of thing but I
haven't really gotten terribly involved
yeah in the deeper stuff when women in
Optics got started I had someone on from
spie and I I have to apologize but I
cannot remember the name right now in
the state I'm in but
uh I think we had I had a number of
downloads that they could download
educational packets too you know about
the organization I think they're they're
probably back in the archives of the
show somewhere and the show goes back I
think it's going in its ninth year now
so uh it's been a while yep well I'm
sure that I I don't actually if you go
through the s spu website you can
probably find their link yeah I don't
know that off the top of my head either
yeah how about some information I'll put
a link to to your website on the page on
the web page okay thank you and uh I
don't know what that's going to do don't
uh don't expect a rush or anything like
that of orders or anything especially
considering the audience that it's going
out to I guess people you know that are
listening to this are basically just in
interested in hearing about triple take
and what you do and things of that
nature but uh I'd like to begin
promoting what I call handcrafted
holography these are folks that are
working
the same as a cabinet maker works or
someone who hand makes a bicycle frame
and they work in their own private labs
in their own Studios and they offer
holograms for sale and I think that's
basically what you're doing you you you
and denesh fall under that handcrafted
holography category you have no no
automation yep well most of holography
doesn't really um the industry hasn't
grown big enough to support people who
make make automation equipment yeah you
know there there's a lot of people that
have made their own for their own
purposes that have then tried to go off
and sell it to other people there are a
couple of those companies around um but
it really is you know all hand done um
apart from you've got the like the dot
matrix machines and everything but that
mostly is you know not really artistic
enough for the people who want to do
this kind of thing they want to do the
whole
three-dimensional you know coming out at
you kind of stuff yeah speaking of
Matrix and and things of that nature do
you do any mastering for emboss tography
at all um yes we do um we don't have the
ability at present to print our to do
the actual embossing but we have made
Masters and then send them out and one
of the things that we're looking at for
next year is you know to see if we can
get some in-house equipment because one
of the other things that a lot of people
seem interested in is you know they they
don't want 5 million pieces to go to
American bank note
you know they want something a little
more personalized and so you know we'd
like to look into doing some more emboss
work in the next year yeah for for short
runs yep is that correct yes yeah yeah
is there since we're coming up on 20
minutes already that's why I usually say
15 to 20 minutes because usually by the
time the show's over it's 30 uhuh I try
to keep the file size is small you know
cuz with everything on the web anymore
you know there's a lot of listeners that
are over in Europe and Asia believe it
or not there's a there's a school a
school a girl school a science School in
China that listens to this it's a it's a
girl school oh good I mean it's all over
the place and uh but I the thing is the
the longer the show I'd love to do long
shows but the longer the show the bigger
the file size and it's it's incredible
to download this stuff anymore Y is
there anything that you'd like to
mention that I did not ask about um let
me think about what we've gone through
my goodness just about
everything what would your advice be to
students that would be out there that
might be or anyone for that matter that
might be thinking about doing holography
as a business because you probably get
emails all the time I get emails all the
time with you know people that have
ideas for the next big thing and um what
would you say to someone yeah I would
think that if you're trying to make a
business of it you have to get outside
of yourself because when you're doing a
business of any kind even if you're
providing a product you're still really
providing a service and one of the
things that Hal ographers frequently do
is they're so enamored of their own
technology that they don't recognize how
other people see it that's an excellent
very that's an excellent
point and one of the things when I the
very first holograph that I met face to
face was actually Dan schweer M um then
the production holographs at ABN of
course and and he really was a big
inspiration to me because what I saw him
doing was stepping outside of just the
medium and seeing what you can do with
it he liked to play with the images
floating in space and he took little
little steel models and and interacted
with them and he really was looking to
see what he could pull out of it and not
just what can I do with it and I think
that was really something that I've
carried with me along the way and I hope
I can live up to that
I think Dan had a background in theater
didn't he stage stage work or something
but you can see it in his work yeah yeah
I'm not sure if that's correct or not I
I spoke with Dan a number of different
times and for some reason that uh that
sticks with me Dan Dan was going to do a
holot talk interviewing me before he
passed away oh and we never we never got
around to doing that and I never sought
any I never sought out anyone else to do
it since then cuz Dan was the guy that
uh that was going to do it s like a good
idea that show May Never
air so we were we we did we grow up
close to one another I was from Philly
yeah um I actually grew up in Cherry
Hill New Jersey get out of here my
wife's from Belmore yeah yeah in fact
I'm probably going to see my mom for
Christmas no kidding he still lives
there H Cher when I first went out
looking for holographs and I made some
phone calls and I don't know if you
might have been actually one of the
people I called when I came out of
college um looking for jobs oh was told
that there are no jobs we're all
independent people working out of our
basements yeah huh that that would have
been something I would have said in a
nice way of course yeah they did tell me
some of the other things that were going
on in holography and not just art but
also in Technical holography and I think
that inspired me as well because have
one foot in the technical world oh or it
might have been you it might I don't
remember who it was yeah I know that I
learned originally um I had gotten a
book from a friend of mine when I was a
kid it was uh Jeff burner's holography
book and in the back of it was a bunch
of interviews with the old holographs oh
and so that's where I started and
started calling people around that were
local to me and I know I talked to Ken
Dunley he right there in Philadelphia as
well I know I talked to a second person
and I can't remember who it was and it
may well have been you may have
been yeah Cherry Hill did you ever go to
Cherry Hill Mall all the time yep me too
work there a few times did you get out
of here yeah I my my wife and I when we
first started dating we're we're
together 30 years this year and when we
first started dating we went to a
restaurant down at the airport circle
called the pub uhhuh and uh we always
like to travel down there and have
dinner down there and also stop uh like
a Cherry Hill Mall and things like that
so the mall the mall is still there yes
it is yes it is that's I think isn't
that supposed to be one of the first
malls on on the East Coast that's what I
kept telling people in one of the
cornerstones it's in starbridge and clo
right down there where the fountains
were I think it said like 1961 or
something uhhuh yeah used to go over
there when I was a kid they used to have
a summer concert series with the with
the uh pops Orchestra uhuh right there
by the fountains and we used to sit
there and listen to all the show tunes
and all stuff like that yep yeah it was
a great
place all right Joy anything else um no
I think that's good now people will be
living listening to this probably 20
years from now I guess that would be
nice yeah I don't know if if the same
people are still in the business 20
years from now that'll be interesting
we're we're in it for a long time yes
indeed yeah
jeez all right well you have a very nice
holiday you too do you celebrate
Christmas yes I do well Merry Christmas
Merry Christmas to you and uh please
tell denesh I said hello okay and uh I
have to get together sometime yep all
right we'll be up there
probably and see if we can get some time
in for you okay I have to give a call
all right you take care thank you for
being on the show and taking the time
you're welcome thank you for having me
thank you bye
bye